<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Roberto Esteves</title>
    <link>http://robertoesteves.dev/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Roberto Esteves</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 15:30:00 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://robertoesteves.dev/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I think I&#39;m not fine</title>
      <link>http://robertoesteves.dev/posts/social-anxiety/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 15:22:16 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://robertoesteves.dev/posts/social-anxiety/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My mental health have been deteriorating over these months and I&amp;rsquo;m worried that
it&amp;rsquo;s getting worse. I can&amp;rsquo;t help but observe the absurds I see during my day and
how radicalized the world have become. I genuenily fear those people that mock
others because their views and beliefs are different than theirs, going as far
as gaslighting the person entirely. I&amp;rsquo;m no innocent for doing that at some point
of my life, but I try to redeem myself and start to have a better construction
of words where someone don&amp;rsquo;t be harrased by me and have a more civil discussion
about important things that are generally disregarded because it doesn&amp;rsquo;t match
their views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those super skeptical people that might think I may be on a extremist group
of some kind, I want to warn that &lt;strong&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m only speaking on behalf of myself, and not
for some group of any kind.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;everyone-needs-help-not-just-a-selective-minority-group-of-people&#34;&gt;Everyone needs help, not just a selective &amp;ldquo;minority&amp;rdquo; group of people.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s important to say it out loud, because some people just don&amp;rsquo;t get that
everyone have problems in their lives. Just because someone is a &amp;ldquo;cisgendered
white male&amp;rdquo;, doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that he can&amp;rsquo;t have any form of physical or emotional
support. Judging a person solely because of their appearence is just wrong, and
it creates a flammable debate about &lt;em&gt;why group X is the root of all evil in this
world&lt;/em&gt; that in turn radicalize individuals and distance them from each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, despite being considered a &amp;ldquo;cinsgendered white male&amp;rdquo;, I still have my
struggles. I have severe ADHD that makes learning very hard for me. Paying attention
for a consecutive amount of time is hard and any distractions makes me deviate from
what I need to do for hours. I&amp;rsquo;ve been learning how to better control it since
the pandemic, but sometimes I can&amp;rsquo;t just help myself. I really try, but it&amp;rsquo;s just
not enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite all my struggles, I&amp;rsquo;m happy on what I achieved to learn about programming
and computer science in general. I really love computers and I try to push it for
being my source of living in the future. I&amp;rsquo;m also grateful for having proper conditions
to live a life with dignity and so much more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-i-cant-feel-any-good&#34;&gt;But I can&amp;rsquo;t feel any good&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still feel my life is miserable. I can&amp;rsquo;t see myself on the goals I try to push
and say for my friends and family. I can&amp;rsquo;t feel joy for doing things that I would
enjoy months ago. My only desire I have after work is going to bed and try to sleep,
but failing miserably because I still keep using my cellphone. I would even skip
some classes at college for that. I would even try to oversleep to not go at work,
but I know I&amp;rsquo;m needed there and also I need to do something at least productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-plans-doesnt-go-as-expected&#34;&gt;My plans doesn&amp;rsquo;t go as expected&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I planned from moving to another place have been delayed because of college, which
seems fine at the start but I can&amp;rsquo;t see any importance of it anymore. My class has
a lot of people that brings unorder and chaos. They don&amp;rsquo;t care about learning and
the content, but about partying and using drugs, just like any university student
nowadays. Having a 18-22 year gap from others is a lot for zoomers, like I can&amp;rsquo;t
even understand some of the things they&amp;rsquo;re taking about. They seem to care more
about their social media life than real life itself. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be friends
to this kind of people, they care more about the physical part of life too much,
where I try to balance between the physical and spiritual/emotional parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;im-burned-out&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m burned out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t live my life like this anymore. I want a break from everything. I want to
rest for whatever amount of time I need to return with sanity. I want to feel joy
again like I have been feeling in the past months. &lt;strong&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t stay here doing nothing
to make my life a bit better and rot for years.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m also tired of trying. My persistance seems to have come to an end, for now, but it
also might be just a need to cool my mind off for some time. Still, I feel like I suck,
and those that attack people just by their appearence or believes affect me a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to believe in a world where I might be able to make a difference and also
a better place for everyone, but this agressive and radical dialogue about the
opressor and the opressed makes me feel like shit. &lt;strong&gt;If that&amp;rsquo;s what they wanted,
congratulations to them.&lt;/strong&gt; I feel like I&amp;rsquo;m not entitled for help and by doing that
would expose me to evil people that would exploit me and get away from it because
they&amp;rsquo;re a &amp;ldquo;minority&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have different visions about how to make life and society better and end most
social pathologies, but with this kind of behaviour I see at college, friends and
social media, it makes me feel hopeless, like I&amp;rsquo;m not entitled to talk about it because
&amp;ldquo;you&amp;rsquo;re not them, so you can&amp;rsquo;t speak on behalf of them&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;you can&amp;rsquo;t interfere with the
life of others, we live like we want!&amp;rdquo;, but then proceeds to dictate how a group
of people should behave, otherwise it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;opression&amp;rdquo;, even for the same group of
people they say they&amp;rsquo;re defending against the opressors. I&amp;rsquo;m not denying &lt;strong&gt;legitimate
opression&lt;/strong&gt;, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean we should take sides too early in case of a
crisis because one side is more opressed than the other, but to proceed to think
and rationalize a solution to the problem instead of just fighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to make anyone feel bad. I&amp;rsquo;m feeling bad at this very moment,
and I don&amp;rsquo;t want anyone to be passing what I&amp;rsquo;m feeling right now. But I&amp;rsquo;m tired
from anyone cutting bonds with anyone that disagrees from him, and goes as far as
gaslighting them and getting people cancelled because of something stupid like a
opinion. People that pretend to be weak do a lot of work behind the scene against
those that disagree with them are either evil or really needs to seek professional
help. I don&amp;rsquo;t have any empathy with them and I hope that your acts have serious
consequences in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I legitimately feel fear for someone falsely accusing me of something and then
proceed to exploit the system for their own gain. That happened to me before,
and I don&amp;rsquo;t want to feel that again. That&amp;rsquo;s why I don&amp;rsquo;t want to talk and expose
a lot of myself to other people. &lt;strong&gt;I fear them, even my friends I have fear.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know for how long I will be feeling like this, but I hope it ends as soon
as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Muista Development - Part 0</title>
      <link>http://robertoesteves.dev/posts/muista-development-part-0/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2023 14:20:15 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://robertoesteves.dev/posts/muista-development-part-0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been learning finnish since 3 years ago, starting with language learning apps
(specially the green owl one), Youtube videos and also TV shows from the country,
at which point I decided to get enrolled ina course where the embassy of Finland
in Brazil recommended (always send your questions to the local embassies of a
country that you have interested to learn their language, they are generally
receptive and tries their best to answer your questions!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I find very difficulty to get familiarity with words in the language,
despite getting exposure to them a lot of times. I tried to use anki, a really
good flashcard software used a lot to memorize new words of a language, but the
biggest flaw I believe is that you only memorize the word at it&amp;rsquo;s own, not the
meaning that it has on a certain text. That becomes a lot more obvious with sentences
like &lt;strong&gt;Kuusi Palaa&lt;/strong&gt;, that can mean:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The spruce is on fire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The spruce returns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number six is on fire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number six returns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Six of them are on fire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Six of them return&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your moon is on fire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your moon returns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Six pieces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s just a lot of things to memorize for a single sentence, and it&amp;rsquo;s not this
particular example! Finnish has a lot of single words with multiple meanings that
depends on the context. In short, using anki to learn languages isn&amp;rsquo;t very
effective for finnish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why I had an idea, what if I create a program where the user can put any
text inside of it, then it can mark words that he wants to memorize (also annotating
other things like the normal form, type, etc&amp;hellip;) and later it has a quiz where
it shows the word, the additional annotations and the whole sentence where this
word was marked initially?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why I want to create a new program called &lt;strong&gt;Muista&lt;/strong&gt;! I had a lot of attempts
of trying to create this type of program, but I always struggled to conform with
user experience, developer experience and what I believe it&amp;rsquo;s the best for the
desktop world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m opposed to the modern way to do desktop development, which are only an instance
of Chromium/Webkit running an HTML page with CSS and ECMAscript. It might be good
for UI and security, but it becomes a burden when you want to interact with the
underlying system below it. When I tried tauri, using something like SQLite was
painful because it made me code the same data model &lt;em&gt;twice&lt;/em&gt;, and the IPC communication
via tauri commands results in &lt;strong&gt;frequent Serialization/Deserialization of JSON&lt;/strong&gt;, making
the program much slower if you try to stream megabytes of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I also wanted to be cross-platform! So a lot of frameworks like GTK (yes, I
know you can use it on Windows and MacOS, but it leaves a lot to be desired on
these platforms), WPF and others aren&amp;rsquo;t suitable. After lots of time choosing,
I decided to use the same GUI library that anki also uses: &lt;strong&gt;Qt&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has good support on most operating systems, it&amp;rsquo;s very mature and have the performance I desire
for my program. A lot of people says it&amp;rsquo;s very bloated, but even it being a fair
criticsm, it&amp;rsquo;s what I also liked about it: it has SQL support and a lot of widgets
to make complex interfaces. I believe it&amp;rsquo;s going to be a good library to use for
this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a lot of work to do, specially designing and prototyping it, so in the next
days I&amp;rsquo;ll be focusing my time in development of this application. I hope you&amp;rsquo;re just
as excited as me :).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My First Post!</title>
      <link>http://robertoesteves.dev/posts/my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 15:22:15 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://robertoesteves.dev/posts/my-first-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;hello-world&#34;&gt;Hello, world!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is going to be my first time where I can talk about a bit of what I most
enjoy doing in my day-to-day basis. I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading other people&amp;rsquo;s blogs and
articles for a long time and I always had a will that one day I&amp;rsquo;ll try to share
what I&amp;rsquo;ve been discovering and studying. I took inspiration from
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drewdevault.com/&#34;&gt;Drew DeVault&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m an IT student located in Brazil that likes software development, especially
systems development. It&amp;rsquo;s very possible that I will mostly talk about free and
open source software since I believe it&amp;rsquo;s beneficial to everyone that uses
software, compared to other types that restrain their users freedom for the
sake of profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of things I will talk about in this blog:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software development in *nix systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Systems programming in Go, C and Zig&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Idioms and Cultures (especially Brazillian and Finnish)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My vision about the world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Future events that I might participate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks a lot for reading this, and I hope you&amp;rsquo;re just as excited as me to see
what&amp;rsquo;s this blog will be in the future!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
